Finding Aid for Palmer Family Papers, 1853-1940
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Palmer Family (Pontiac, Mich.) Papers 1853-1940
Palmer family (Pontiac, Mich.)
2 linear feet
Orchard Lake, Michigan, family, with various business interests, including lumbering and land transactions (in Michigan, California, West Virginia, and British Columbia), and also active in the development of the Orchard Lake area, especially from the 1920s to the 1940s; Correspondence files of individual family members, subject files detailing family interests and activities, business and legal records, maps, blueprints, and photographs.
8978 Aa 2
The Palmer Family Papers document the activities of an upper-class Michigan family in nineteenth-century and early twentieth-century Michigan. The collection contains items of both business and personal interest, documenting the business fortunes and misfortunes of Charles Henry Palmer and his family. The collection also offers insights into upper-class family life.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by Todd Golding (donor no. 7249 ) in September 1991; the student notebooks were the gift of Mrs. Palmer Bradfield (Donor no. 665 ). Additional donations by Suzanne DeVine (donor no. 11259 ) in April 2015.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887) was a pioneer investor and developer of mines and railroads in Michigan's Upper Peninsula. Born in Lenox, New York, he graduated from Union College in 1837 and married Betsey Ann Cowles in 1839. After their marriage, they followed his parents to Michigan, where Palmer became principal of the Romeo Academy in 1847. He served on the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan from 1852-1859, and was instrumental in securing his close friend, Henry Tappan, as president of the university.
From his home in Pontiac, Palmer began developing and investing in mines in 1854. He opened the Portage Lake District's first successful copper mine, the Pewabic, and invested in other copper and iron ore mines in the area, among them the Franklin Mining Company and the South Pewabic Mine. He also joined groups of investors to help develop the Marquette, Houghton & Ontonagon Railroad and the Portage Lake and River Improvement Company Canal connecting Portage Lake with Lake Superior.
Charles and Betsey Palmer had four children: Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911), Clarence A. Palmer, Virginia Louise Palmer Pickman, and Philomela Palmer Hoffman.
Philomela Palmer Hoffman was a favorite, cherished aunt to Charles Palmer's (184?-1911) children, judging from comments made about her in the family's correspondence. She continued many of her father's business interests, including managing her parents' estate after their deaths. She also invested in real estate in Pontiac. She married Conrad P. Hoffman, although it is not known whether or not they had children.
Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911), known occasionally as "Henry", continued his father's business interests, in addition to launching many of his own. He was involved with mines in Montana, Colorado, and Mexico and actively traded stocks on the Eastern exchanges. Palmer married Mary Elizabeth Spalding Palmer, with whom he had at least one child, Elizabeth Virginia Palmer Bradfield, known as "Bessie".
In addition to continuing some of her father's business interests and managing his estate after his death, Elizabeth Virginia Palmer Bradfield was a sculptor, and traveled to Paris in 1896 to study sculpting. She married Thomas Parks Bradfield in 1896, with whom she had at least two children, Virginia Palmer Bradfield Ward and Thomas Palmer Bradfield.
Virginia Palmer Bradfield Ward married Harold Lee Ward, establishing the Palmer family's connection with the Ward family of Orchard Lake. Her brother, Thomas Parks Bradfield, graduated from Michigan College of Mines in Houghton as a mining engineer, and spent several years working in South America. He married Esther Gourd in 1924, but they were divorced in 1926.
The Palmer Family Papers document the activities of an upper-class Michigan family in nineteenth-century and early twentieth-century Michigan. The real strength of the collection is the documentation of the growth of early business in Michigan. The Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887) series contains the bulk of this information, with papers documenting his activities as an investor in mining and railroads in Michigan's Upper Peninsula from the 1850s through the 1880s. Although Palmer was a regent at the University of Michigan from 1852-1859, the collection contains no items documenting that experience, with the exception of photostatic copies of letters from University President Henry Tappan, 1853-1872. The balance of the collection contains items of both business and personal interest, documenting the business fortunes and misfortunes of family members, and offering insights into upper-class family life. Only two of Charles Henry Palmer's (1814-1887) children, Charles and Philomela, are documented in this collection.
Subjects:
Astrology.; Capitalists and financiers--Michigan.; Eastern Railroad Company.; Mines and mineral resources--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Palmer, Charles Henry, d. 1911.; Pontiac (Mich.); Railroads--Michigan.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Travelers.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Women capitalists and financiers--Michigan.; Wood, De Volson, 1832-1897.
Contributors:
Bradfield, Elizabeth Palmer.; Palmer, Charles Henry, 1814-1887.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887)
  The Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887) series is divided into two subseries: Correspondence and Topical files.
  - Correspondence
    Almost all of the correspondence (7 folders) is incoming and concerns Palmer's business interests in Northern Michigan. The items from the 1850s document the establishment of the Pewabic Mine and the efforts of Palmer's associate, William Heywood of Boston, to sell the stock to investors on the mining exchange there. The 1860s correspondence continues to address mining investment, as well as stock exchange prices and procedures, employee compensation, and real estate purchases. In addition to mining, the Palmer correspondence of the 1870s and 1880s documents railroad investments, real estate transactions and subsequent tensions between local interests and Eastern investors. Palmer's personal correspondence (1 folder) contains letters from his father, sister and brother. Of particular interest, because of the era, is a letter written by Palmer's father during the Civil War (1863). Four letters are unsigned, some are undated. This series also contains a small number of photostat letters form Henry Tappan, discussing Tappan's travels in Europe and business relating to his stock trading with Palmer.
    - Business Correspondence, 1853-1859 (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1860-1869 (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1870-1872 (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1873-1879 (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1880-1887 (Box 1)
    - Business Correspondence, 1862-1877, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1863-1887 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Henry Tappan, 1852-1872 (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical File subseries contains legal and miscellaneous items relating to Palmer's business interests, such as court documents regarding a lawsuit against Palmer from a former employee, J.S. Prall, records of deeds of land in the Upper Peninsula, and abstracts of titles clarifying Palmer's link to the land he originally owned in Oakland County. Additional miscellaneous items are also included.
    - Ledgers and Deeds (Box 1)
    - Legal Transactions (Box 1)
    - Real Estate Transactions (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Ledger Books, 1867-1877 (Box 2)
- Mary Elizabeth Spalding Palmer and Spalding Family
  Mary Elizabeth Spalding Palmer and the Spalding Family contains correspondence to and from members of the Spalding family. Additionally the series contains Mary's diaries and correspondence, the diary and correspondence of Jedidiah Spalding (Mary's father). There is also correspondence from various Spalding members such as Lyman A. Spalding (Mary's brother), Sally Ann Harrington (Mary's mother), and Annie Spalding (Jedidiah's sister).
  - Mary Elizabeth Spalding Palmer Diaries, 1893-1899 (Box 2)
  - Jedediah Spalding Diary, 1822-1901 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1867-1895, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Betsey A. Palmer (1822-1898)
  The Betsey A. Palmer (1822-1898) series (2 folders) contains correspondence to faimly in Montana and relating to settling the estate of her husband, Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887), who died intestate.
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1887-1899 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898 (Box 2)
- Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911)
  Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911) (5 folders) contains correspondence regarding business transactions and miscellaneous items. The correspondence between Palmer and his father (1 folder) addresses their mutual business interests in Michigan, namely the Marquette, Houghton & Ontonagon Railroad, the Pewabic and Franklin Mines, and other stock interests. The letters contain a good deal of business advice from father to son, but little other information of a personal nature. The other correspondence in the series (3 folders) documents Palmer's business transactions regarding his investments in mining, real estate, and trading of stocks and bonds. The miscellaneous file in this series (1 folder) contains some items of interest: Photocopy of the 1896 entries of the diary of Mary E. Palmer, Palmer's wife; two of Palmer's notebooks from the University of Michigan; miscellaneous deeds and indentures.
  - Correspondence between Charles Henry Palmer (1814-1887) and Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911) 1871-1881 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (General) 1887-1899 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1900-1902 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1903-1911 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Philomela Palmer Hoffman
  Philomela Palmer Hoffman's series includes correspondence and legal papers regarding her interests in mining and real estate investments. Additionally, the series contains papers from the settlement of her mother's estate (1 folder). The Cornucopia Mine file (1 folder) contains legal documents and correspondence regarding the gold mine in Utah in which Hoffman, her sister Virginia, and her brother Charles, invested. Like her father's correspondence, these letters largely document the means of trading and maintaining mining interests in the early twentieth century.
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1903-1927 (Box 1)
  - Cornucopia Mine, Utah, 1877-1905 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Land titles and deeds, 1867-1929 (Box 2)
- Elizabeth Palmer Bradfield
  The Elizabeth Palmer Bradfield series contains documents similar to those in her Aunt Philomela's series, namely correspondence with family members concerning business transactions (1 folder) and legal documents regarding the Steward Iron Mining Company (1 folder). Much of the correspondence concerns the estate of her father, Charles Henry Palmer (184?-1911), and the family's real estate holdings prior to and at the time of his death. Additionally, Bradfield maintained her own interests in mining investments, and this series contains relevant legal documents and correspondence. This series also contains photocopies (two folders) of Bradfield's diary from May 31, 1895-Dec. 31, 1896. These diaries describe in detail the daily activities of an upper-class young woman, and provide some information on other Palmer family members. The diary also describes her 1896 visit to Paris with her parents to study sculpture with the artist Julien, as well as her marriage to Thomas Bradfield in October of that year.
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, 1892-1936 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Steward Iron Mining Company, 1888-1940 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1897 (Box 2)
  - The Detroit Tribune Society pages, 1913 (Box 2)
- Thomas P. Bradfield and Virginia Palmer Bradfield
  The Thomas P. Bradfield, Jr. and Virginia Palmer Bradfield series (1 folder) contains a number of miscellaneous items that provide information about the Palmer family in the twentieth century. In addition to correspondence between Tom and his sister Virginia, his mother and grandmother, the collection contains photocopied excerpts of Virginia's diary from January 2 to January 21, 1922. The diary is very short, and does not provide the same level of insight into typical daily life as her mother's 1895-1896 diary offers. This series also contains a letter and a court deposition regarding Tom's divorce from his wife Esther in 1926.
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1896-1926 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series (2 folders) contains a colorful file on astrological information for several family members (1 folder).
  - Astrology (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (1 folder) contains photographs of members of the Palmer and Spalding families.
  - Photographs (Box 2)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library holds the Ward Family Papers and the Edmond DeVine Papers.